ILGWU. Carl Proper papers 5780/150
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Carl Proper papers
1979-2001
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Proper, Carl
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/150
38.83 cubic feet
38.83 linear ft.
Reports, correspondence.
The papers of Carl Proper consist primarily of subject files and files on labor-management committees.
5521567
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Carl Proper was Executive Assistant to President Jay Mazur and Executive Director of Council on American Fashion.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
Z. Owen, August 05, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, June 19, 2014
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Proper, Carl.
5521567
- I. ILGWU (Box 1)
- AFL-CIO Boycotts, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  List of companies being boycotted by AFL-CIO, with cover letter from Mazur urging that the ILGWU honor the boycott
- AFL-CIO Committees, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  List of AFL-CIO standing and ad hoc committees with ILGWU participants and those with no ILGWU participants, March 8, 1988; list of all AFL-CIO standing committees and members, Nov. 6, 1987
- Apparel Industry: Statistics, Union Membership, 1960-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Memo to ILGWU president David Dubinsky from Research Dept. re analysis (attached) of union membership in relation to U.S. Census figures, Jan. 22, 1960; statistics for total ILGWU membership, as percent of women's and children apparel production workers, and percent change for each year, 1961-86; census statistics for production worker employment 1972, 1977, 1982 by geographic region
- Apparel Industry: Competition (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Affidavit by ILGWU director of research Herman Starobin in litigation against ILGWU by Levi Sportswear, claiming union cartel, 1984; excerpt from Governor's Advisory Commission final recommendations on the cloak, suit and skirt industry, New York City, re rise of jobber-submanufacturing system, 1926; Federal Register notice re 1984 Merger Guidelines, Dept. of Justice Antitrust Division; U.S. Census statistics
- Apparel Industry Development Program: NYS (2 folders), 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  Letters from ILGWU president Mazur and CAF director Carl Proper to NYC deputy mayor Barry Sullivan and NYS legislators urging support for a $1 million line item in the state budget for establishment of an apparel industry development program, including a technology extension service that would position the state for a federal manufacturing extension center; text of proposal; schedule of events for visit to state capital; memos; handwritten notes
- Associate Membership, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Report of the Task Force on Associate Membership, which proposed a new category to assist in organizing efforts: associate membership would be offered to workers where organizing campaigns had failed, and to those who left their jobs, in order to maintain contact
- Benefit Funds, 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Report of the Benefit Funds Department to the General Executive Board, Feb. 2, 1988; Report of the Task Force on Vacation and Holiday Funds, Oct. 1987; memos re drug plan, re Benefit Fund Payments, Mar. 8, 1988; letters from retirees expressing gratitude for drug plan, 1991-92; fact sheet, Health Services Plan, comparison 1990/1991, notes 1990 "crisis," "high users"; health fund fact sheet with history of fund mergers, 1986-92; articles summarizing benefit plans, printed in Justice, 1988
- Benefit Funds: National Retirement Fund, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  National Retirement Fund fact sheets, c. 1991; actuarial report as of January 1, 1991, by Martin E. Segal Company; estimated employer withdrawal liability for Steffen Manufacturing Co. through plan year 1990; Charles Weinstein Coat Co., Inc., calculation of partial withdrawal; ILGWU National Retirement Funds Report of Withdrawal Liability as of Dec. 31, 1991; newspaper clipping
- Benefit Funds: Union Health Center, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Printed history and description of the Union Health Center, in New York City, excerpted from Breakthroughs in Health-Care Management: Employer and Union Initiatives, by Victoria George and William E. Hembree (c. 1986, Health Research Institute, Pergamon Press); note from physician for ILG official Herman Starobin, Nov. 15, 1988
- Commentary: Articles & Testimony, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Articles and testimony by ILGWU officials: ILG president Jay Mazur testimony before House Ways & Means Committee re Reagan's new tax proposals, June 13, 1985; interview with Mazur as new president, 1986; interview with Mazur by Bureau of National Affairs re trade legislation, 1988; description of ILGWU: membership composition, history through Carter administration; Report of Research Dept. re imports, March 10 Sept. 10, 1984; "Endangered Labor Market," by v.p. Evelyn Dubrow and Herman Starobin in The Journal/The Institute for Socioeconomic Studies, summer 1984, warns global telecommunication will erode U.S. intellectual advantage just as globalization has undercut U.S. industry in other arenas; "Trade, Investment, and Deindustrialization: Myth & Reality," by ILG president Sol Chaikin, in Foreign Affairs, September 1982; "The Other Economy," by Gus Tyler, in New Leader, 1978, American Labor Conference on International Affairs
- Commentary: Articles & Testimony: Presidents Columns, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Columns by President Mazur in ILGWU Justice
- Commentary: Office of Technology Assessment, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Critical 6-page analysis by James Parrott, Ph.D., executive assistant to ILGWU president Jay Mazur, on the U.S. Congress Office of Technology Assessment's report "U.S. Textile and Apparel Industry," March 1986; also notes report by ILG Research Department re women's and children's apparel industry and imports, sent to OTA study author
- Computer Data Processing Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Minutes and handwritten notes from meetings of the General Executive Board's Data Processing Committee, 1989; Computer Services Department Report to the Data Processing Committee, March 28, 1989; Data Processing Evaluation Study prepared by Arthur Young, c. 1988
- Computer Project Subcommittee: Organizing Department, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Initiated as a subcommittee of the Data Processing Committee to improve the ability of organizers to obtain information on companies, campaign efforts, and workers, explained in July 20, 1990, memo from exec. asst James Parrott; Report of the Organizing Department Computer Project, Feb. 26, 1992, prepared by exec. asst. Parrott; minutes of organizing directors meeting, April 1990; minutes and handwritten notes from meetings of the Data Processing Committee, 1992; report by Ernst & Young, "Data Processing Evaluation Study," January 1992; comments on study by ILG exec. asst. Parrott
- Computer PC Subcommittee: Database Management, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Minutes of the PC Subcommittee, 1993; guidelines for accessing master files; printouts
- Computer Database Software, 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Correspondence and descriptive literature about Grassroots PLAN, designed for labor union legislative and political action work; brochure from AT&T for get-out-the-vote software
- Computer Database: CAF, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Lists of union apparel manufacturers and other categories; memos
- Drug Testing, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  ILGWU Policy Statement on Drug Testing, opposing random drug tests either for pre-employment screening or to monitor current workers, recommending treatment rather than punishment, and off-duty privacy rights (intervention only when on-the-job performance is impaired), n.d.; draft statement with handwritten notes; printed publication, "Drug & Alcohol Testing on the Job: Safety with Personal Dignity," an AFL-CIO Guide, c. 1987; American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME) publications: "The Drug Testing Debate: Remedy or Reaction?" 1987, and "Questions and Answers about Drug Testing in the Workplace," 1986; OCAW Reporter article by president Joseph Misbrener, "Labor Must Counter Drug Testing Treat," March-April 1987
- Earned Income Tax Credit Campaign, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  General Executive Board special meeting materials (agenda, remarks by president Mazur); information sheets for ILGWU staff members; coordinators' training session materials; IRS tax preparation instructions; correspondence with the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities; invoices, financial records related to campaign costs
- Electoral Politics (Endorsements), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Memo from v.p. Evelyn Dubrow to President Mazur re meetings with five members of the New York Congressional delegation, recommending whether to endorse each individual or run other candidate against him, October 1, 1986; memo to all NYC managers and NYS district director from Mazur, explaining endorsement of Mark Green for U.S. Senate against Al D'Amato, October 14, 1986
- Financial Report, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Garment Industry Task Force, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Task force to coordinate exchange of information among existing ILGWU representation on industry-related bodies in New York. Meeting minutes and agendas, newspaper clippings; discusses activities particularly of the New York Garment Industry Advisory Committee (see also), real estate issues
- General Advisory Council, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Fact sheet describing GAC: created in 1984 by ILG president Sol Chaikin, composed of mid-level ILG officers and directors not members of the General Executive Board; list of GAC members; first and second meeting minutes, February 1, August 26-28, 1985; agendas, handwritten notes, March 1986; meeting minutes, August 19-21, 1986, discussing organizing strategies, need to raise pay for union organizers, need to target new (non-apparel) industries and overseas workers, possibly merge with other unions; printed report, "The Changing Situation of Workers and Their Unions," by AFL-CIO Committee on the Evolution of Work, February 1985; list of roll call votes on HR 1562, Oct. 10, 1985 and Dec. 3, 1985, and Senate vote, Nov. 13, 1985; 1986 Campaign Strategy Sheet: list of Republican Senators up for re-election, profile of each, including voting record on key issues; AFL-CIO Legislative Alert special report, "The Gramm-Rudman Law: How It Works And Hurts," Feb. 3, 1986
- General Advisory Council, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Printed report re deindustrialization: "Crossroads of America: Choosing a Better Future for American Industry and the American People," with cover letter from ILGWU president Jay Mazur, sent to GAC members in preparation for campaign against imports; "Time to Raise the Minimum Wage," testimony by pres. Mazur to the Congressional Roundtable, Congressional Research Service, May 20, 1987; meeting agendas, handwritten notes from meetings; AFL-CIO guidelines for pre-endorsement activities by members in presidential campaign; survey of membership in preparation for 1988 election; memo re establishment of new Dept. of Associate Membership; presentation by Carl Proper re Council for American Fashion, Needle Trades Action Project (MA), and Lehigh Valley Apparel-Textile Project (PA), November 13, 1990; minutes of meeting by ILGWU exec. asst. James Parrott; suggested agenda/talking points (memo from exec. asst Parrott to Mazur) for October 26, 1990 meeting; Mazur agenda/talking points for September 24, 1991 meeting; summary of meeting, including discussion of 1992 convention, reports from committees
- General Executive Board: Minutes, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Restricted. Includes summary of major decisions of the board at 1986 meeting.
- General Executive Board: Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Restricted
- General Executive Board: Minutes, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- General Executive Board: Minutes, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- General Executive Board: Minutes, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  Restricted. Report by strategic planning consultant Klein & Co., Cambridge, MA; includes presentation to ACTWU General Executive Board
- General Executive Board: Retreat, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Restricted. Handwritten notes from GEB retreat, July 21-22, 1992; list, ILGWU Goals, with letter from vice president Paul Winslow, Central States Region, correcting list of goals
- Industry Development Working Group: Minutes, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Committee of the ILGWU General Executive Board; surveyed best practices of unionized apparel industry. Memos, minutes of meetings, handwritten notes, newspaper clippings
- Industry Development Working Group: Surveys (2 folders), 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  Surveys of manufacturers and contractors, memos
- Health and Safety Department, 1983-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  "Safety and Health in the Garment Industry," description of activities and structure of the department; "Health and Safety Hazards in the Garment Industry," prepared by department; newsletter, Update Health & Safety, Dec. 1987- Jan 1988; brochure, "Is Your Job Making You Sick?" with cover letter by New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health (NYCOSH), July 1988; "Using Health & Safety in Organizing," summary of two ILG organizing campaigns; research papers: "Motion-related wrist disorders traced to industries, occupational groups," by Roger C. Jensen, Bruce P. Klein, and Lee Sanderson, Monthly Labor Review, September 1983, "Understanding Statistics on occupational illness," by Harvey J. Hilaski, and "The job safety law of 1970: its passage was perilous," by Judson MacLaury, March 1981; testimony of health & safety director to county legislature in support of protection for video display terminal (VDT/computer) operators; AFL-CIO Right to Know Teleconference agenda, April 23-24, 1987; flyer re video, "A Price for Every Progress: The Health Hazards of VDTs," Labor Institute; "Women Workers: Hazards on the Job," from AFL-CIO American Federationist, August 1978; "Information Access: Health & Safety Documents You Have a Right to Under the Law," by department, n.d.; contract between department and NYS Dept. of Labor, July 1, 1988, to create an ergonomically redesigned "model shop" and conduct conferences and training sessions in English, Spanish, and Chinese; memos and press releases from U.S. Department of Labor re new OSHA proposals for formaldehyde, 1991; newspaper clippings, 1988-91
- International Relations Department, 1987-1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Brochure, "What in the World is the ILGWU Doing?" prepared by the department; letter from pres. Mazur to Chemical Bank president protesting loan to South African company Minorco, Mar. 6, 1989; report, ILG Program for Textile and Garment Unions re assisting black trade unions in South Africa; ad copy for Johannesburg Star by New York Labor Committee Against Apartheid; letter from Mazur to Nicaraguan president Daniel Ortega protesting harassment of union members, July 28, 1988; First Summit of the Textile and Apparel Unions of the Americas to Analyze Social and Economic Integration in the Western Hemisphere: No Integration without Labor Participation, Sept. 2-5. 1991, Caracas, Venezuela; briefing memos to Mazur re visiting international delegations from Cyprus, Egypt, Indonesia, United Kingdom; Joint Statement of Fifth Joint Conference of ZENSEN (Japanese Federation of Textile, Garment, Chemical, Mercantile, and Allied Industry Workers' Unions) ACTWU ILGWU, Kyoto, Japan, November 26, 1987; letter from ILG organizer in Upper South Dept. re international solidarity, December 23, 1988; resolution by California Labor Federation asking ALF-CIO to change its policy to permit contact between U.S. unions and unionists of all other nations (including socialist) without government interference; International Confederation of Free Trade Unions weekly summary, re New Zealand's outlawing of unions, with hand notation by Mazur, March 21, 1991; letter to Mazur from the Committee to End the Chinese Gulag, July 19, 1991; minutes of subcommittee of International Labor Organization, March 24, 1988
- Invoices, 1988-1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Invoices: Books (2 folders), 1988-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
- Invoices: Subscriptions, 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Legal Department, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Report of Legal Department to General Executive Board, re Supreme Court reviews, March 10, 1984, September. 14, 1984, January 10, 1985, June 24, 1985; printed report by department to convention, Labor Law and ILGWU Cases re hostility of Reagan administration to labor movement (in convention proceedings, March 7, 1986)
- Locals & Affiliates, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Memo proposing Guide to ILGWU Departments and Affiliates to be modeled after attached NYS Banking Department, July 22, 1988
- Canada (2 folders), 1984-1991 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  Reports, newspaper clippings, press releases, and correspondence between the ILGWU and its Canadian affiliates re imports, NAFTA/free trade, and homework. Report to the General Executive Board, January 18, 1991, submitted by Gerald Roy, Canadian director, ILGWU; "Conditions in the Women's Garment Industry: Canada," March 12, 1984, prepared by the ILGWU Research Dept.; background paper, "Canada in Crisis" by Willis Armstrong, director, the Atlantic Council of the United States; paperbound book, It's Not Free! The Consequences of Free Trade with the U.S., by the Ontario Federation of Labour; ILGWU Pre-Feasibility Study on "Toronto Sews," August 8, 1989; government report, "Assessment of Direct Employment Effects of Freer Trade for Ontario's Manufacturing Industries," prepared by the Ministry of Industry, Trade and Technology, November 1985; Ministry of Labor proposed changes to Cabinet Submission re reform of the Labor Relations Act, August 12, 1991; newsletters: Ontario Labour, quarterly magazine of Ontario Federation of Labour, 1985-86; Union Fabric, ILGWU Ontario District Council, 1986-89; brochures re occupational safety and health, racial harassment, homeworkers' rights; newspaper clippings
- Canada: Quebec, 1984-1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  "Study to the Consultative Commission on Working Conditions," presented by the Joint Council of Quebec of the Union Internationale des Ouvriers du Vetement pour Dames, Montreal, December 12, 1984; annual report, 1989-90, Quebec Federation of Labor Solidarity Fund (Le Fonds de Solidarite des Travailleurs de Quebec); Terms of Settlement between the Quebec Joint Council of the ILGWU and the Quebec Fashion Apparel Manufacturers' Guild (n.d.); discussion paper, "The FTQ-CLC Relationship and Quebec Politics, July 7, 1992; French-language edition of ILGWU newsletter Justice, December 1990; newspaper clippings
- Central States, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Central States Region Report to the General Executive Board, February 1988; TV news clip transcripts, newspaper clippings; newsletter, DCWU Local 399 (Evansville, IN) News 'n Views October/November 1989; correspondence
- Eastern Pennsylvania, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Correspondence re possible training programs, April 27, 1990; newsletter, Union News, December/January 1989
- Midwest, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Report on homework/sweatshop operations in Chicago, July 10, 1986; newspaper clippings re black women in the labor movement (Labor Research Review, Spring 1988, #11), fading leftist activism among youth ("Activism among the Yuppoisie," Norman Atkins, Village Voice, Feb. 24, 1987), Labor '87 News re Chicago Federation of Labor endorsement of Chicago Mayor Washington
- New England, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Letter of resignation from organizer, with impressions of ILGWU reputation in Massachusetts, especially among electronics workers, December 29, 1987; text of presentation by Carl Proper before TWARO seminar in Malaysia, and trip report, September-October 1986; text of television segment re garment industry in Massachusetts, WBZ-TV (NBC), March 7, 1991; correspondence; newspaper clippings
- New Jersey, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Faxed memos to ACTWU president Jack Sheinkman re Liz Claiborne settlement, July 8, 1988; memo from director of New Jersey Region to ILGWU general counsel Max Zimny re agreement with Alexandra Fashions, North Bergen, NJ, and Fairbrook Enterprises, NYC, April 12, 1989; newspaper clippings
- New York City Local 10, 1976-1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  "The Union and Cutting Contractors," submitted to the General Executive Board Committee on Local 10, Jay Mazur, February 10, 1976; collective agreement, New York Coat, Suit, Dress, Rainwear and Allied Workers' Union with New York Coat and Suit Association, Inc., and Infants', Children's & Girl's Sportswear and Coat Association, Inc., 1985-88; yearly membership census, 1983-87, with percent decline, wage averages, and arguments against wage cap; statistics about high health service plan usage, May 9, 1988; list of membership census for all ILGWU locals, comparing 1988 with 1985, and percent change; correspondence
- New York City Local 23-25, 1987-1992 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Newsletter, Local 23-25 News, 1987-90; Local 23-25, ILGWU, Report to the General Executive Board, January 1988; letter from ILGWU exec. asst. James Parrott noting that Chinatown manufacturers were not interested in exposing themselves to the publicity or scrutiny of nomination for the Labor Commissioner's Award, which was set up to improve the image of Chinatown, Feb. 11, 1992; journal clippings
- New York City Local 62-32, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Newsletter, Our Union, with note to ILGWU exec. asst. James Parrott, Winter 1990
- New York City Local 89-22-1, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Contract summary and brochure, "Welcome to the Union!" (both in English and Spanish); newsletters, Local 89-22-1 News; memo re outreach to deaf members, May 2, 1990
- New York City Local 99, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Newsletter, Local 99 News, 1986-88
- New York City Local 102, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Resolution re restructuring, August 15, 1988
- New York State, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Transcript of testimony by ILGWU director of NYS District at hearings on child labor held by the NYS Dept. of Labor, July 27, 1988
- Northeast, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  Speech script, Northeast Staff Meeting, September 13, 1989
- Puerto Rico, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Newspaper, NACLA (North American Congress on Latin America)'s Latin America and Empire Report re U.S. unions in Puerto Rico, May-June 1976; newspaper clippings
- Southeast, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 25)